so in terms of the like 32 parts of the
body you can't
see your brain your lungs intestines
Etc so
that when
you think about
it when you want to contemplate your
brain your
lungs then that idea is there that thought is
then that idea is there that thought is
there but it is that so now I'm
attending that
thought and then I'm picking up the sign
of those things yeah well that that's
there's a difference there that's
exactly the only way people would people
would approach this the only way they
would know how is through
attending in other words they will be
attending that thought as if that's
really attending to your brain which you
can't so the only way to see these body
parts correctly in in the relevant
contemplation manner is indirectly
without attending them directly as
objects of your attention you have to
discern them as that because of which
you are here living attending to
things so that's the difference where
people well that's the difference
between doing the body contemplation
rightly and wrongly wrongly is basically
just just repeating these parts and
visualizing them and thinking that
that's somehow I mean it might provide
you initial kind
of
um reduction of central craving because
you never think about those things but
soon very soon you'll get used to it and
it will become meaningless cuz you can't
you can't see those things directly
that's why in P the the Salat the six
sense space is the ultimate indirect
it's the ultimate peripheral it's the
ultimate that because of which there is
the world for you you are perceiver you
are the conceiver of it that's why when
when the when the Buddha describes these
the six the six sent space it's
described in that almost external
medical manner the fleshy eye the nose
and so on cuz that's that's the the
closest you can see it you
can't you can't see directly you cannot
attend to your eye you can only attend
to the
object but that's not the eye because of
which you see
things but you misconceiving it that
that's the eye because of which you see
things you start assuming that you can
attend that because of which your
attention is
there so you have to stop trying to
attend the eye the nose but start
Discerning it as a basis as a physical
basis for the world to exist for
you but then so in the same sense like
you can be attending at the cup
attending at the
table attending at the image of your
brain and but you're just regarding
these things as overly objectified
objects of your attention so to
speak in a way they have something in
common they are all material but you
don't want to regard your brain just as
you regard a cup because cup is
insignificant to
you you want to discern that that
objective brain that you are thinking
about is the reason for your
subjectivity because of which you're
able to attend to the idea of the brain
in the first place so so what you just
said said there must I keep saying that
to myself and again say that to myself
well you might have to initially to
remind yourself to to kind of recreate
the the the right order of things that
you can dwell on
it but after a while you don't have to
after while it would be enough just to
because you will know how to look
indirectly you will know how to see
things without having to look at them
and that's another thing I think people
might misund misunderstand in these
uh the the the talks on YouTube and and
stuff when we mention you know the
simultaneous presence people might end
up thinking it's like a two things at
the same time momentarily present in
front of
me but when I say simultaneous presence
uh the way the sutas talk about it it's
basically two things are present on two
different levels which means they're not
there equally present uh at the same
time for a second or two and you must
catch them both at the same time no
you're just just trying to catch one
thing again you can divide it into
million of subp Parts your attention is
still looking at that foreground of an
object so when we talk about
simultaneous presence that's why I keep
saying it endures the peripheral endures
which means in this case say you have a
you have a an image of your brain that
you don't overly attend as a random
object in the world that you tell them
to yourself see this body is not mine no
you see that image of the brain you stop
misconceiving it as the W would say and
you start Discerning it that's the
closest the closest you can get to that
which actually your life depends upon to
that form the closest you can get is
through these images of the brain lungs
heart blood and so on you realize all of
them stand for that because of which you
are conscious here living this life but
you can't possibly enter that brain as
in access it through your perception or
anything like that because it precedes
it but you can know that the image of
the brain that you have that on that
peripheral level is that because of
which you able to again be here and now
present and attend to these various
other things that
arise in other words then when you stop
thinking about the brain your knowledge
that that's the order of your experience
as in you are undermined by the matter
doesn't change and that's what I mean
it's simultaneously present you don't
have to keep think you can you can
forget about it rightly it will
basically will constitute rightful
forgetfulness which is when your
forgetfulness does not induce a anymore
but you don't have to keep think you
it's impossible to keep thinking about
everything all the time yeah that's what
I that's what I think sometimes you have
to do you have to cuz you can't really
think okay brain exactly exactly cuz you
just keep them make forcing it into
foreground and then you fail to see what
what what the peripheral that is which
means you you have now overly
misconceived that brain and you're
making it into an object of your
perception which is impossible for it to
be eye cannot see
itself but because one wants
to let me just say like this I want to
add this so like say you think about the
brain right peripheral you discern the
image of the brain and you recognize
there is the brain in here because of
which my experience still exists and
then you stop thinking about it and then
3 hours later you think about it again
and it's important here to to to induce
the attitude if you have to eventually
you will recognize it as such it's
important when 3 hours later you think
about a brain again you recognize that
it's the same
brain that has been here this whole
time the fact that you forgot about it
did not make it not
there so then even like same like with
moods or feelings say you have a present
mood orison it's it's it's sort of I
don't know agreeable but then you know
you you start attending to more
particular things doing and then you you
don't go around thinking how agreeable
your day is but then later four 6 hours
later you sort of look back and you
remember it again it's agreable it's the
same mood and that's what I mean you
have to let it endure basically that
means that when you bring it back you
don't make it yours but you recognize it
as it has been enduring on its
own that's how you start Discerning the
simultaneous principle I'm talking about
simultaneous in a sense that yeah the
general mood the general notion of the
matter being there for example in the
contemplation of the body it's been
there enduring on its
own whether you thought about it or not
so when you do remember you you will
eventually stop giving priority to I
remember this and I'm attending this and
I'm practicing this you just find it
yeah so it's it's simultaneously present with
so it's it's simultaneously present with
everything else you do when you don't
attend to that it's the necessary basis
basically for your action for your
choice for your
attention when can you uh because
obviously you want to develop the domain
as you say you want to develop the
domain that
background domain
MH
so one wants to then
develop it okay I've got nothing to do now okay
it okay I've got nothing to do now okay
I'm going to develop that but
then Le I forget about it yeah you
develop it by learning how to discern
that it's already there sure but
then then you you have to forget about
it yeah after a minute after a minute
that's fun then when you remember about
it you want to abandon the attitude of I
must restart this this practice because
I forgot about
it but instead you want to develop
recognition oh yeah it's still
there that's pretty much the crucial
difference that I'm talking about where
because many people say be here now be
present just feel just this it's just
like that and whatnot but it all
revolves just come back to the present
moment come back to the present moment
you want to recognize that when you come
back to the present
moment you could only do so because it
was there enduring beforehand it was
always there so then you realize you
can't forget about it even if you
want you are responsible for your own
ignorance cuz you are responsible for
the attitude of thinking it's on you to
hold it in front of you and that's the
only way of existing so you you forget
about it after a minute then you
remember it after five minutes and then
you think oh crap I forgot about it I
must I must do it again now as if you
were the one who does it from the
scratch no so each time that attitude arises you
no so each time that attitude arises you
include that attitude in that
mindfulness as
well it's not rooted in you it's rooted
in the enduring background it's and
that's what the mind is by the way the
ultimate background chanita and that's why he
background chanita and that's why he
knows the mind and exalted or is shrank
or is depressed or is elated these
states that people obviously almost
automatically appropriate are the states
of mind as such is ured 5 days later you
you remember it again the only reason
you can remember it is because it's
still there
enduring to some
extent and what will that do this kind
of practice of mindfulness can you
cannot just well you can't be threading water
just well you can't be threading water
with it if you keep doing it it it is
forcing you basically to shift the
center of your experience from your
sense of self onto the background of the
things and even the actual things that
you're attending because you realize
that they are there because of the
background in other words you start
squeezing your own sense of s out there
is no room for it in the experience CU
whether you look at the background
whether you're attending the foreground
you realize this it can be done so only
because these things endure on their own
beforehand and in terms of the
peripheral as I said six days later you
remember something it's because for six
days it's been enduring there
the state of
mind so that's how you stop woring about
I must not forget I must not forget but
instead start focusing on I must discern
whenever I remember I must not
misconceive whenever I remember and the
most fundamental misconceiving is mine
as in I am here the center not this
thing that I remember because of which I
am in the first
place so whatever okay so whatever you
your mind whatever you attend to at any
given time that must induce a
remembering of the of the way things are
well you don't even have to say like
that you can just say whatever you
attend to just be aware of um of what
you're doing so include yourself in that
doing so include yourself in that
picture and that with that sense of self
is that's already where the background
is but now instead of instead of sort of
feeling that each time you remember you
must restart and then hold as long as
you can you drop that whole attitude or stop
can you drop that whole attitude or stop
paying attention to it but instead
whenever you remember even if it's once
a day on a day that you very distracted
you still don't try to like oh now I
remember I must hold it no I remember it
is already there Arisen beforehand not
mine not for me not myself cannot be
mine and that automatically affects
everything else within that background
within that
peripheral but it's going to take time
to see that cuz now the emphasis is on
what I attend that's what matters so
that's why you try to keep okay so I'm
attending onto this I'm attending onto
this then you forget and you think oh
now I have to do it again no you
don't because the only reason you can
attend to anything is is because it's
there given as an option which means it
exists on the peripheral where the
possibilities exist so practically speaking you think
exist so practically speaking you think
about your brain your heart your lungs
you can attend to it directly if you
want but don't misconceive it don't
think that it's that re that really
which heart is it's an
approximation that you determine whether
it's going to be right if you don't
misconceive it or wrong if you
misconceive it so practically you think
about there is this brain there is this
bone bones there this Senus there is
this flesh and that is the reason for me
flesh and that is the reason for me
being able to look at these bones
Senus so once you start attending to it
correctly there's the heart the lungs
and so on that's it you you don't have
to try to keep it in front of you
because it's not in front of you you're
looking at this that which determines
your experience as you know it the the
necessary condition for it which is
presence of the matter
so once you brought it to your mind you
do so in order to let it
go you don't have to you want to learn
how not to have to actively think about
it in order for it to be regarded as
it's present it's
real so you think about these various
parts of the body as the as the reason
for your experience and then you let it
let it be and then say you're still
mindful of it like we can do it now
think about your
heart and then give you the significance
in the sense of don't just think about
like a picture of a heart but think
you're beating heart right now that you
can actually feel
beating have do you have any volutional
power over it can you say can you tell
it to slow down can you tell it to speed
up no can you tell it to stop can you
tell it to never stop can you tell it to
not get sick can you tell it to not get
blocked and clothed up none of it which
means it's utterly inaccessible to you
yet now at the same time think about
what if that heart were to stop now
would you be able to remain alive you
wouldn't so your whole life right now
while we're talking about depends on
something well basically depends on your
heart in the same sense that it depends
on a random ticking clock in the world
they have no control over that ticking
clock stops your heart your heart
basically stops that's what it
is and that's it so you don't have to
like I must keep attending this I'm now
you already set up the experience allow
it to
endure so now your mind might move
further there's a cup of tea or coffee
but if I ask you now 15 seconds later
the perception of the significance of
your heart that has been now left to to
drift into that peripheral it's still
there you haven't forgot it cuz I
haven't forgot it cuz we've been talking
about it
together and we can be silent a bit
longer talk about something else but
actually see there is still a threat
there the heart we spoke about like 30
seconds ago now that phenomenon is still
there we are not attending to it yet
it's still there you haven't completely
lost it and then the time will come when
you will completely lose it and that's
the important point or forget about it
yeah that's what I mean when you forget
about it when you go back to it you go
back to it in the same manner as it is
enduring now not as something I must I
must I must overl attend this no it's
already there it's already determination
for your
life whether you tell to yourself that
or not doesn't matter so you want to
stop having to tell that to yourself and
you want to start learning how that
thing will tell it to you because things
are gener genuinely impermanent and
cannot be owned and cannot be
controlled but you can't see that
because you depend on you telling
yourself that things are genuinely
impermanent cannot be owned and so on so
yeah you have to start like that but you
have to see that it has to come from the
thing not from you and you will see that
if you allow thing to endure so it's
been a minute and a half
now the perception of the significance
of the heart is still there isn't it it
faded but it's still
there that background connection so to
speak hasn't been lost although we
already went through three different
topics on top of it but it's still
there it's still enduring on the General
peripheral level in both our minds
actually you know that that's that's my
whole point it's not like some I don't know
point it's not like some I don't know
spiritual intuitive knowledge no it's
the clarity of phenomena you know no
that's what we've been talking it's
enduring there you can attend to all
sorts of things but that thing is still
there on its own that's the important
bit that's how you stop putting the
emphasis is that's how you shift it onto
the phenomena that has arisen and
enduring not onto me attending
it that's how you place yourself second
basically and when the sense of self is
second it's not a sense of self anymore
sense of self is always the first the
master so at the background of your
mind the perception of the significance
of the beating heart we we spoke about
it is it still there it is isn't it
it's not gone and there hasn't been a
single active effort made I must bring
this back
no but what what what we did do is
clarify the significance of it and now
it's
enduring you set it up rightly and now
it's enduring and it's still there
actually all this time it's pisting the
same thing is persisting while it's
changing on all this particular level
through through discussing all these
various things and that's what mean
things we're discussing now are
simultaneous present with the background
that's enduring that it's a different
thing from
them they change a different speed but
they're simultaneously there they don't
connect they don't merge they're simply
two things
standing one in the background from
where you look which means if your
attention looks at one side is going to
be on the other side that's just how it
works that's why you can choose signs
that's why you can look at this or of
that because the options are
because the options are
given I might stop thinking about other
things whatever you start thinking about
other things you use the same principle
of allow your mind to get established
upon the significance of that peripheral
and then let it go let your mind think
other things see now is there still
significance of the heart present it
is and I know it is I know it is in your
mind as well and I and I can't enter
your brain and read your mind but I can
see the the phenomenon that we
established but what it it did change a
bit it faded even more now because our
topics are taking us further from it so
we keep introducing the new significance
and then what's going to happen is when
you look back and think about a
significance of the heart it's going to
arise as a
memory as in the enduring phenomena has
ceased and then you realize now you have
the experience of what was the enduring
phenomena which now is enduring and
that's how the same significance of
these perceptions can be reestablished
at a finger
snap because you don't have to go
through the same motions and methods to
re it's already implied in it you just
need to clarify your
discernment it's still
there so you have to keep on topic you
say you have to keep on topic if you CH
you to the extent yeah but basically
establishing that significance rightly
would sort of create that enduring
context but you don't have to keep this
is the context this is the context this
is the context context context no it's
there you let it
endure and then what do I do then you
don't do anything you let your mind
think just make sure it doesn't go into
sensuality ill will and cruelty that's
it that's all you have to do just
prevent it from going there if he
doesn't want to go there you don't have
to do
anything that's how you make your own
sense of self redundant e for